

# Ksenija Kovalenka

#### **Profile**

Enthusiastic and dedicated undergraduate physics student willing to enhance existing skills and gain knowledge in the research sector. Possesses outstanding numeracy and observational skills gained during studies together with important time management abilities. Independent and fast learner, capable of taking responsibility and performing a given task fast and precisely.

#### Education

#### Physics MPhys, The University of Manchester

SEPTEMBER 2019 — PRESENT

Current grade average: 80 %

Aimed grade: 1st Class Master's Degree

Relevant Courses (to be completed by June 2022):

Condensed Matter Physics, Mathematical Fundamentals of Quantum mechanics, Advanced Quantum Mechanics, Electrodynamics, Quantum Computing.

#### John Leggott College

SEPTEMBER 2017 — AUGUST 2019

Graduated with three A\* and best student award for one of the subjects.

## **Relevant Projects and Academic Experience**

### Independent research projects

AUGUST 2019 — SEPTEMBER 2021

Variational Quantum Eigensolver Algorinthm and its Applications. (implemented in Python, Qiskit; 2021)

Studied Hartree-Fock theory to determine the ground state energy and separation of the hydrogen molecule. Performed the same calculation using variational quantum eigensolver on the qiskit statevector simulator.

Modelling vibrational modes in solids, classical interpretation. (implemented in Python; Physics Institute of Science and Technology; 2020)

Studied tight binding problem in 2D lattice to solve for energy bands for different configurations analytically as well as using Python script.

Modelling Free Fall and Viscous Laminar Flow. (implemented in Java; 2019)

#### **Laboratory projects**

JANUARY 2020 — DECEMBER 2021, THE UNIVERSITY OF MANCHESTER

Nuclear Magnetic Resonance, Franck-Hertz experiment, Properties of Gamma Radiation, High-Resolution Gamma-Ray Spectroscopy.

Developed essential experiment planning, recording, and presentation skills. Presented unique and creative solutions to solve the upcoming issues. Utilised Gaussian and Poisson distribution statistics to interpret data and fit corresponding theoretical models using computation. Practiced both written and oral scientific communication.

#### **Personal Details**

ADDRES

23 Anson Road Flat 2 Manchester United Kingdom M14 5BZ

#### CONTACT INFORMATION

- +447809763384 (UK)
- +37067776313 (LT)

ksenija.kovalenka@student.manchester.ac.uk http://linkedin.com/in/ksenija-kovalenka

2000/12/21

#### **Computational projects**

SEPTEMBER 2020 — JUNE 2021, THE UNIVERSITY OF MANCHESTER

Monte Carlo Techniques Penetration of Neutrons Through Shielding. (implemented in Python, Jupyter)

Numerical Integration of Differential Equations: The Damped Harmonic Oscillator. (implemented in Python, Jupyter)

Measuring Spreading Law: using curve fitting to experimental data to determine spreading law for picolitre droplets. (implemented in Python, Jupyter)

Doppler Spectroscopy: analysis of exoplanets using function minimization. (implemented in Python)

Gained strong programming skills and mastered their applications in data analysis, simulation, and presentation. Progressed in code debugging and performance optimisation. All projects completed to a high standard of required style and efficiency.

## **Other Experience**

#### Physics and Maths Tutor, MyTutor.com

SEPTEMBER 2019 — PRESENT

Developed strong interpersonal skills, practiced presenting and conveying ideas. Improved organisation and time management skills due to a freelance nature of the role. Gained many satisfied reviews and valuable feedback.

#### **Supernovae Foundation Member**

APRIL 2021 — PRESENT

Joined an organisation helping young women to pursue a career in physics. Attended webinars on general skill training such as time management or productivity and engaged with the community to develop communication skills.

## **Volunteering and Social Impact**

#### Dig Deep Kenya

OCTOBER 2021 — PRESENT

Currently involved in fundraising for the residents of Kenya to have access to clean water and hygiene via organisation of various events and campaigns.

#### **PASS leader**

SEPTEMBER 2020 — JUNE 2021

Assisted learning of a group of first-year students to help them settle well into the university environment and achieve their academic goals.

#### **Horse Sanctuary summer volunteer**

JULY 2018

Duties involved handling, training, and basic care for rescued horses, site maintenance.

#### **Skills**

Software and programming: Python (Proficient), C++ (basic), Java (basic), LaTeX (basic), Microsoft Office. Languages: English (Fluent), Russian (Native), Lithuanian (Fluent).

#### Other Interests

Horse riding, Polo, Visual Arts.